- Mr Rivers.
-里弗斯先生
- Oh, good morning Matron.
-早上好，护士长
- Good morning.
-早上好
- How is your patient?
-你的病人怎么样了？
Dr Saunders would like a word with you.
桑德斯医生想和你谈谈
Is something wrong?
出什么事了吗？
The doctor's waiting in his office.
医生在他办公室等您
Ah, Rivers, good morning.
啊，里弗斯，早上好
I've been waiting for you.
我一直在等你
How is my wife?
我妻子怎么样了？
Your wife is no longer in the hospital.
您的妻子已经不在这所医院里了
Your wife has left our charge.
您的妻子离开了我们医院
She's disappeared.
她消失了
When Sister went in this morning,
she was gone.
护士长今早查房的时候，她已经不见了
Are you trying to tell me that
she went home by herself... in her state?
你是想告诉我她自己一个人回家了吗？以她现在的状况？
I'm trying to tell you, Rivers,
that she left of her own accord.
里弗斯，我是想告诉你，她是自愿离开的
We don't know when, we don't know where.
我们不知道她是什么时候离开的，也不知道她去了哪儿
I knew she was rotten from the first day I saw her.
我第一天见到她的时候，就知道她不简单
Raman?
拉曼
Raman!
Gopi?
戈皮
Abraham?
亚伯拉罕
Gopi?
戈皮
Olivia?
奥莉维亚
Olivia.
Douglas was married again soon after the divorce
道格拉斯离婚后不久就再婚了
and to someone far more suitable than Olivia.
娶了一个比奥莉维亚更适合他的女人
He produced a whole lot of little empire builders I believe.
我相信他们膝下有很多小的帝国建设者
That was the trouble with Olivia,
这也是他和奥莉维亚的矛盾
he kept telling her she wasn't enough of an empire builder,
因为他不停地告诉她，她不足以当帝国的建设者
she wasn't a proper memsahib.
她不合格
You don't look like one either,
你看起来也不像
not that they breed them anymore.
不像是他们抚养的后代
I say is this thing still on?
这个东西还开着吗？
Oh no, the tape's run out.
没有，磁带到头了
Yes, I suppose nowadays you just go out there
是啊，我想现在这个时代你只要出去
to follow some guru or something.
采访一些古鲁领袖或者其他的事就可以了
Is that what you are doing?
这就是你现在的工作吗？
No of course not, of course not.
不，当然不是，不是
See, she was outraging two con ventions,
你知道的，她违背了双方的约定
those of her own people, and those of the Indians,
一方是她自己的国家，一方是印度
whose con ventions are, if anything, even stronger.
如果发生什么事，就看哪一方更强大了
And of course you can 't do anything...
当然了，你不能做任何事情
Thanks awfully, Harry, you've been absolutely wonderful.
哈里，多谢你的帮忙，你是个大好人
God knows what indiscretions I committed,
天知道我许下了多么不理智的承诺
what beans I've spilt.
如果一切还很重要的话
If it matters a hoot anymore.
谁知道我揭开了谁的伤疤
Oh, look, this is you.
哦，看，这是你
You've kept all those letters Olivia wrote to Marcia, have you?
你保留了奥莉维亚写给玛西亚的所有信件，对吗？
Yes, of course.
是的，当然了
You know, you don't look like Marcia used to,
你知道，你不像玛西亚年轻的时候
not one bit.
一点儿也不像
No, I suppose women have changed,
不对，我想女人们是会变的
it's not like it was.
变得和以前不一样
Your grandmother carrying on in Paris.
你外祖母在巴黎生活
Olivia in India.
奥莉维亚在印度
My goodness but they were romantic,
你很难相信，但她们都很浪漫
all for love and that sort of thing.
一切都是为了爱情
You've got better things to do now I dare say, hmm?
我敢说，你现在有更重要的事情要去做
Oh...
哦
I don't know.
我不知道
What?
什么？
- Speak up.
尽管说出来吧
- Well.
好吧
The same, you'd better be careful out there.
同样的，你在外面要小心点儿
I hope you've had all those injections one has to have.
我希望你已经打了所有该注射的疫苗
I wouldn't like to see you going to Satipur without them
我可不想你没有注射这些疫苗就去赛提普
or to Khatm.
或者哈塔姆
Anne, always remember,
安，你要永远记住
every old India hand will tell you the same thing...
每一双印度老人的手都告诉你同样一件事
no water, ever, anywhere.
那是一个水资源匮乏的地方
That's golden rule number one.
这是黄金法则一
And no uncooked foods, no fruit, no salads...
只有煮熟的食物，没有水果，没有沙拉
golden rule number two.
黄金法则之二
I always wanted to research,
我一直想去调查
search out what happened to Olivia.
调查奥莉维亚发生了什么事
She was my grandmother Marcia's sister
她是我外祖母玛西亚的妹妹
and wrote long revealing letters
写了很长的披露性信件
which my grandmother gave to my mother, and she to me.
我外祖母传给了我妈妈，我妈妈传给了我
But now I'm getting involved not only in Olivia's life,
但我现在不仅走进了奥莉维亚的生活
but in others, like the family I board with.
还走进了其他人的生活，比如我住宿的这家人
Namaste.
（印度语）你好
And sometimes the two are difficult to reconcile.
有时候这两种生活很难协调
We're beginning to look slightly civilised.
我们要看起来稍微文明礼貌一点儿
Mrs Crawford, the collector's wife,
克劳福德太太，收税员的妻子
the Burra Memsahib,
布拉夫人
came to inspect me in my nest today.
今天来我家视察我的生活
I don't think she thinks much of me...or the nest,
我认为她对我和我的房间的评价并不高
but she's very tactful.
但她非常的圆滑
She told me she knows how difficult the first year always is
她告诉我，她知道第一年总是最艰难的一年
and if there was any little thing
甚至是很小的事情
she could possibly do to ease things for me,
她都会尽可能地减轻我的负担
well, I must just consider her to be always there.
那我只能认为她会一直在我身边了
I said "thank you", demurely.
我非常有礼貌地说了，谢谢你
Actually, her being there is the only difficult thing,
事实上，她的存在才是唯一困难的事情
otherwise everything is just too perfect.
否则一切就太完美了
If only I could have told her that.
要是我能告诉她这些就好了
Sir Rufus Mackleworth,
有请觐见者
Mr James Crawford,
詹姆斯・哈佛德先生
Major Arthur Minnes.
梅杰・阿汤・明尼
It's not what you're used to.
你之前可不是这样子的
Oh, it's far better than what I'm used to.
我现在比之前好多了
But don't you like a chair or a table, some curtains?
但你看起来不就像铺着窗帘的椅子或者桌子？
Curtains?
窗帘？
I'd much rather look out.
我倒想看看
- Did you understand that?
你听懂了没有？
- No.
没有
She said the food is ready.
她说食物已经准备好了
"Bhojan" means food.
那个词就是食物的意思
"Bho" - it's like with a "bo" and a "huh" - bhojan.
发音有点儿像波和哈
- Please take your rent.
请收下
- Oh, there's no need really but...
真的不需要，可是
So bhojan...
食物已经准备好了
Bhojan?
食物？
The social circumstances are such...
社会环境就是这样
Ritu?
瑞图
That...
这样
We really have no choice.
我们也没有办法
Anne?
安？
I'd be interested in knowing your opinion on early marriages.
我很好奇你对早婚的看法
I don't know anything about it, why don't you ask Ritu?
我完全不清楚，你为什么不问问瑞图呢？
She's not used to talking with people very much.
她不太喜欢和人交流
House.
房子
Oh, that's better, that's lovely.
这条更合适，真好看
This is very good, very good, loose, it's good.
非常好看，非常好，松一点儿，很好
How do I look?
看起来怎么样？
You don't have to come with me, I am all right,
你不用跟着我，我不会有事的
really I am.
真的不会有事的
I... oh, dear.
我，哦，天啊
I was going to the post office and I thought I'd wait for you.
我正打算去邮局，我以为要等你呢
- Here.
给
- No thanks.
不用了，谢谢
You know, I can't get over the fact
你知道吗？我不敢相信
that your office is in Olivia's bungalow.
你的办公室就是奥莉维亚的家
In fact, I think...
事实上，我认为
...that you're right in what was her drawing room.
你正好在她的会客室办公
Uh huh, come on let's go.
额，上来咱们走
- What's wrong, Inder Lal?
怎么了，英德尔・拉尔
- It's okay.
没什么
Look, I know there's something wrong.
听着，我知道出事了
- Do tell me what it is.
请告诉我出什么事了
- It's nothing Anne.
安妮，没事
- It's nothing.
真的 没事
- Oh, you must please.
不，请你一定要告诉我
Look, there's so much I want to talk with you about
听我说，我想和你说很多事
but these people they're just ignorant,
但是，这里的人真的太无知了
they don't know anything.
他们什么都不懂
They just, you know, they think the reason
你知道的，他们只是，他们觉得
you've been waiting for me all this time
你一直等我的原因是
is that it's sexual, that's all they know.
你喜欢我，这就是他们的想法
Oh, my goodness, I didn't even think about that.
天啊，我都没往那方面想
I'm so sorry.
我这的很抱歉
Why should you be sorry?
你为什么要道歉呢？
They should be sorry.
他们才应该道歉
They're just ignorant fools.
他们就是一群无知的笨蛋
Just the other day I heard of an incident
就在前几天，我听说了一个
with an English lady in Muzzafarnagar.
关于一个在穆扎夫那格的英国女人的传闻
It was her dhobi, Mrs Rivers.
里弗斯夫人，据说她
Her own washerman.
和她家的洗衣工
He was ironing her undies.
当时他正在熨烫她的内衣
Of course, got excited.
当然了，就兴奋起来了
In a way you can't blame them, it's their constitution,
从某种角度看，你不能责怪他们，是他们的性情
and all that spicy food they eat, it heats the blood.
还有他们吃的火辣的食物让他们血脉沸腾
Well, what is it now?
这又是什么？
Oh, my goodness.
我的天啊
They only have one thought in their heads Mrs Rivers,
里弗斯夫人，他们的脑子里只有一个想法
and that's to...
那就是
you-know-what with a white woman.
你知道的，他们对一个白种女人的想法
Have you seen our darling's grave?
你见过我们孩子的墓地吗？
- No.
还没有
- Come.
来吧
We got the statue, that angel over there,
我们在那边立了一个天使的雕像
from an Italian marble cutter settled in Mirat.
是由米兰的意大利大理石雕刻而成的
It's beautiful.
很漂亮
My baby was beautiful, too.
我的孩子也很漂亮
Every day I tell Willy, "let's go home".
每天我都很威利说，咱们回家吧
I know I can't have my baby back, but let's go.
我知道我不能让我的孩子重生，但咱们走吧
Come, come, Joan.
琼，不要哭，振作点儿
You mustn't do that.
你千万不能这样
This is the worst season for it, that's when then heat's starting.
天气开始变热的时候，就是她最伤心的季节
As soon as we get her off to Simla
我们会尽快送她去西米拉
she'll be as right as rain, won't you old girl?
她就不会伤心流泪了，对吗，我的老太婆
My mother keeps asking, "Why isn't Anne married?"
我妈妈不停地问我，安妮为什么不结婚？
I don't know what to tell her.
我不知道该怎么回答她
What should I tell her?
我该怎么回答她？
Well, oh well, I can tell you.
哦，好吧，我可以告诉你
I did want to, only...
我之前确实想结婚
the person I was with, he was married
只不过我想嫁的那人是已婚
and he kept saying he was going to get a divorce.
他一直说他会离婚的
Then he finally did...
后来他终于离婚了
only he married someone else.
只不过娶了别人
I mean, someone different, not me.
我的意思是，不是我，是别人
Well, no matter, we'll find you an Indian husband.
没关系，我们会给你找一个印度丈夫的
- Ah.
啊
- A very nice, rich Indian husband.
一个富有的善良的印度男人
And then you can live here and have a lot of Indian children.
这样你就可以留着这里，还会有很多印度宝宝
- Would you like that?
你想要那样吗？
- What, children?
什么，宝宝吗？
No, you know an Indian husband.
不是，你知道的，像我一样的
Someone like me.
印度丈夫
But you think I'm very ugly, don't you?
但你觉得我很丑，是吗？
- Oh, horrible.
哦，不忍直视
- Oh.
哦
Begum Sahib welcomes you.
女王陛下欢迎大家
She is very happy to meet this...
她非常开心能够会见
Angelic girl.
这位天使一般的女孩
- Angelic girl.
天使般的女孩
- Thank you.
谢谢
Mrs Rivers is the wife of our assistant collector,
里弗斯夫人是我们助理收税员的妻子
and we are privileged indeed to have so charming a couple in our midst.
我们非常地荣幸我们当中有这样一对魅力无限的夫妻
The assistant collector...
助理收税员
- Have you been to India before?
你以前来过印度吗？
- No.
没有
This is absolutely my first time,
这是我第一次来印度
and I couldn't be more thrilled.
我非常地激动
How long have you been married?
你结婚多久了？
Six months.
六个月
We were married in England
我们是在英国结的婚
but I only followed my husband out here a few weeks ago.
我只是几周前跟随我的丈夫来到这里的
Any children?
有孩子吗？
We were married in September.
我们九月份才结的婚
She hopes that the durbar wasn't too tiring for you.
她希望你不会很无聊
Oh, I loved every moment of it.
哦， 我享受这里的每时每刻
It looked splendid and was so well done.
皇宫看起来金碧辉煌，尽善尽美
It was thrilling to see your son, the Nawab.
我非常兴奋能见到土邦王，您的儿子
I've always like to hear the Khatam national anthem.
我一直都喜欢听哈塔姆的国歌
You must be terribly proud of him, he's terrifically handsome and...
你肯定非常地骄傲，他真的太帅了
How does it go?
怎么唱来着？
He'd cause a sensation in any London drawing room.
他能在伦敦任何一间会客室引起轰动
Olivia?
奥莉维亚？
You know, they think they're frightfully clever,
你知道吗，他们以为自己聪明非凡
but really they're so transparent.
但事实上，他们太容易被人看穿了
- Who?
谁？
- Indians.
印度人
All of them.
所有的印度人
From our right on up to the Nawab, there.
从我们这里的印度人一直到土邦王那里的印度人
They're like children.
他们就像孩子一样
They look like very grown up men to me,
依我看来，他们都是非常成熟的男人
certainly the Nawab does.
尤其是土邦王
Where's his wife?
他的妻子呢？
Oh, she's not here, she ran away and left him.
她不在这儿，她和别人私奔了，留下他一个人
Oh really? Tell me.
真的吗？跟我说说
Oh, I don't know.
我也不清楚
He eloped with her to Paris.
他们私奔去了巴黎
Her family didn't like it so they broke it up,
但是她的家人不同意，他们就分手了
something of that sort.
差不多就是这样
I say, did you see that new memsahib,
我说，你见到我们新来的人了吗？
did you notice her?
你注意到她了吗？
That tall blonde?
那个高高的金发碧眼的女人？
Oh yes, yes.
哦，见到了，见到了
I thought she was a distinct improvement on the others.
我倒觉得她比其他人的态度有明显的改善
- Not that that's saying much.
虽然不是很多
- HE LAUGHS
呵呵
Listen, I remembered another memsahib joke.
听着，我想起另外一个笑话
It's about this Englishwoman that went to the races in Calcutta.
一个柔美的英国女人去加尔各答的比赛
Her shoelace came undone
她的一只鞋的鞋带松了
and when she bent down to tie it up
当她俯身系鞋带的时候
a jockey came along and plonked a saddle on her.
一名赛马的骑手经过，给了她一鞭子
Exactly, because she looked like a horse.
当然了，因为她看起来像一匹马
And when her friends all asked her, "My dear, whatever did you do?"
而当她的朋友们问她，亲爱的，你到底做了什么？
She said, "What could I do, my dears?"
她回答，亲爱的，我还能做什么呢
"I came third."
我跑了第三名
Oh, I was talking to Beth Crawford today.
今天我和贝丝・克劳福德聊天
Now they're leaving for Simla at the end of next month
她们下个月月底出发去西米拉
so I asked her to book you a berth at the same time
我求她也同时帮你
on the Kalka Mail.
订了一张车票
It's over night but it won't be too bad, I promise you.
虽然要一个晚上，但我向你保证不会很累
Now the journey up to the mountains is another four hours, but what a journey.
爬上山顶还要四个小时，但想想沿途的风景
You'll love it.
你会喜欢的
The scenery, not to mention the changing climate.
那里风景优美，更别提凉爽的天气了
You don't for one moment think I'd go without you?
你不会真的觉得没有你我会自己去吧？
But Beth will be there, and Mary Minnies.
但有贝丝在，还有玛丽・明尼
They'll take care of you.
她们会照顾好你的
Oh, that's just silly Olivia.
真是傻奥莉维亚
Mother spent four months away from father every year, year after year.
妈妈每年都要离开爸爸四个月，就这样年复一年
She didn't like it either but,
她也不喜欢这样生活，但是
when you're in a district that's the way it has to be.
当你管理一个行政区的时候，生活就是这样的
You have no idea how hot it gets.
你难以想象这里会有多热，你会抓狂的
It can drive you mad.
你会很烦躁，
You'll be irritable, we will quarrel over every little thing.
我们会因为一点儿小事就吵架
I'm not going.
我不去
You don't think I like it any better than you do, do you?
你觉得我很想你离开，是吗？
I'll be bored.
我会无聊死的
I'll be hot, irritable, all right, we'll quarrel...
天气会很热，我会很烦躁，我们会吵架，没关系的
but please don't send me away from you.
但请不要让我离开你
I believe you've made a mistake.
我猜您进错房间了
Olivia.
奥莉维亚
Oh, thank goodness darling, are you all right?
谢天谢地，亲爱的，没事吧
Well I sort of got lost and there's so many doors...
我有点儿迷路了，这里门太多了
- ...and they all look exactly the same.
每个门看起来都一样
- Oh, scrumptious.
哦，亲爱的
I felt like Queen Alexandra driving through Hyde Park.
我觉得像亚历山德拉王后开车穿过海德公园
And you give him a coat, or a trouser, or a shirt, or something to copy.
你给他一件大衣，一条裤子，一件衬衫，或者其他的什么去模仿
One way is to get these little lamps the Hindus have,
获得印度教徒手中小灯笼的一种方法是
and you fold them in the leaves, and you sail them on the water,
把他们折在叶子里，让他们在水中漂浮
and then the croc gets intrigued of course,
接着就会把鳄鱼吸引过来
and pops up his head, bang straight in the eye.
它们探出头来，纾直接撞到了眼睛
Eight or nine months later I heard from Cocksons
八九个月后，我听到了这样的对话
that there's a greasy piece of paper with my name on it,
一封有我名字的谄媚信件
it was sitting in the Peshawar bazaar.
出现在集市上
It was said to be worth 50 pounds sterling.
据说价值50英镑
Of course Major Minnies, of course.
当然了，梅杰・明尼，毫无疑问
An Englishman's word and all that sort of thing.
一个英国人的文字，诸如此类的物件
Doesn't his mother ever come to any of his dinner parties?
他妈妈从来不参加他的晚宴吗？
How could she, what on Earth are you saying,
你想什么呢，她怎么会
with all these men? Not that generation, never.
和一群男人在一起呢？那代人才不会呢，绝不会
What about his wife? I mean when they still lived together.
他的妻子呢？我是说他们以前一起生活的时候
Oh, you know about that, do you?
你都知道了，不是吗？
Here, try one of these, they're a bit sticky but quite delicious.
来，尝尝这个，有点儿黏，但是非常好吃
Did you know her, what was she like?
你认识她吗？她长的怎么样？
Of course, if it isn't terribly secret.
当然了，如果这不是什么秘密的话
Actually, in a way, it was all my fault.
实际上，某种程度上，都是我的错
She was at school in England with a young cousin of mine,
她在英国上学的时候和我表妹玛乔丽是同学
Marjorie, and I took both the girls to a party
我带她们参加他在卡奇酒店
that he was giving at Claridges.
举办的一个聚会
It was all very thrilling and totally out of bounds for them.
她们都兴奋极了，完全地解放自我
And then they both fell in love with him.
她们两个后来都爱上了他
Poor old Marjorie with her stumpy legs, she never had a chance.
可怜的玛乔丽，两条短粗的腿，一点儿机会都没有
- The other one was very pretty, of course?
看来另外一个非常漂亮了？
- Oh god yes, Sandy was a peach.
天哪，当然了，桑迪太招人喜欢了
She was only 16 at the time.
她当时只有十六岁
Twenty years younger than he was, not that that's what bothered her family.
比他小了二十岁，她家人对此并不忧虑
They were trying to get her married off to a Hyderabad prince who was 30 years older.
当时他们正想方设法让她嫁给一位大她三十岁的海德拉巴王子
Of course, he was a much bigger prince than our Nawab.
当然，比我们土邦王大很多的王子
His wife's family had to come and take her away.
她的妻子的家人不得不过来把她接走
There were rumours of poison.
谣言都是以讹传讹
- Good lord.
天哪
- Some said it was the begum
有些人说是因为女王
because she was jealous of her daughter-in-law.
因为她嫉妒她的儿媳妇
She'd already got rid of his first wife years before.
很多年前，她就除掉了他的第一任妻子
But some said it was the Nawab himself
但有些人说是因为土邦王自己
because he'd fallen in love with a dancing girl.
因为他爱上了一名舞女
Of course, no dancing girl ever materialised
当然，所有的舞女都很现实
so it must've been one of those rumours started by an interested party.
肯定是利益相关方散播了其中一种谣言
It had been Sumerca and Keifer and God knows where,
它曾在上帝才知道的萨玛卡和肯佛尔出现过
it had come over the Khyber pass
最后又来到了卡波尔集市上
and was presented at the Peshawar bazaar
据说，在那个集市上
and was still said to be worth 50 pounds sterling.
这封信仍然价值五十英镑
He's heard that story at least six times.
这个故事他至少听过六次了
So have I and I've only been here three weeks.
我也是，而我来这儿才三周
I don't think I could bear to hear one more anecdote
我觉得我无法忍受再听一个
about what happened in Kabul in 13, don't you know, old chap?
1913年发生在喀布尔的传闻轶事了，老兄，你不知道吗？
Sometimes I think I must be the only person in the world
有时候我觉得我的祖父是世界上唯一一个
whose grandfather was not at the siege of Lucknow.
没有参加勒克瑙起义的人了
- Mine wasn't.
我祖父也没参加
- Douglas's was, of course.
道格拉斯的祖父一定参加了
He said, "Work?"
他说，工作？
"You won't have to work for your first year."
第一年你不需要工作
"Oh by the way, Rivers I've got a..."
对了，里弗斯，我已经
He's very good looking, I like him.
他长的很帅，我很喜欢
Oh, do you?
哦，是吗？
So do I.
我也很喜欢
We were just talking about you.
我们刚刚在谈论你
Nothing about good I assure you.
我向你保证，都是好话
The state of Khatm has always been renowned for its hospitality.
哈塔姆一直以好客闻名
Except in the time of the chap, what's his name?
除了那个家伙的时代，叫什么名字来着？
"Ana" something, Pan.
安娜什么，坎
Amanulla Khan.
阿曼努汗・坎
Oh, Dr Saunders, I hope you're not going to hold that against me?
桑德斯医生，我希望你不要因此对我有敌意
It's not fair Dr Sahib.
萨希卜医生，这不公平
Perhaps Your Excellency has not heard the story
也许阁下没有听过我祖先
of my ancestor and the party he gave?
举办宴会的那个故事？
A neighbouring prince, the raja of Mong,
一位邻国的王子，蒙古的王侯
had done something to displease my ancestor.
做了一些事，惹得我祖先不高兴
So he invited the raja and his retainers to a feast.
因此他设宴邀请这位王子和他的家臣
A ceremonial tent was put up,
宴会的帐篷搭建好了
some choice arrangements were made,
一切都安排妥当
and when the guests were seated to eat and drink
当宾客就座饮酒作乐的时候
to their heart's content, just as we are now,
每个人都心满意足，就像我们现在一样
at that very moment Amanullah Khan
就在这个时候，阿曼努汗・坎
gave a secret sign to his men
给他的手下一个暗号
and they cut the ropes of the tent
他们砍断了帐篷的绳子
so that the raja and his party
因此这位王子和他的宴会
were entangled under the canvas.
困在了帐篷里面
When they were trapped there like animals,
他们像动物一样被困住的时候
Amanullah Khan and his men took their daggers
阿曼努汗・坎和他的手下拿起他们的匕首
and stabbed them through the canvas again and again,
一遍又一遍地插进帐篷里
'til there was not one single enemy left alive.
直到没有一个活口留下来
They still have that tent, Mrs Rivers
里弗斯夫人，他们现在仍保留着那个帐篷
and the blood is so fresh and new
鲜红的血液
it's as if it had only happened yesterday.
仿佛一切发生在昨天
The cause of this enmity was something very small.
这次仇恨的起因是非常小的事情
A trifling, one could say.
可以说是微不足道
The raja had broken his word over a marriage contract,
这位王子违背了婚约
not with Amanullah himself but with one of his followers.
不是和阿曼努汗，而是和阿曼努汗的手下
It was a question of honour
这是名声问题
and Amanullah Khan was not the man to sit quietly
当阿曼努汗・坎或者他的手下被羞辱的时候
when he or anyone of his was insulted.
他绝不会坐视不管
Your Excellency, ladies and gentlemen,
阁下，女士们，先生们
to the King Emperor.
敬英国国王和印度皇帝
- The King Emperor.
Rivers is going to the village of Rampur in the morning.
里弗斯明早要去兰普尔的一个村庄
They've been threatened with a raid.
一群盗贼威胁要发起袭击
Retaliatory raid.
报复性的袭击
Obviously one of the villagers informed on the gang.
很明显有村民向他们告密
They kill a few people, break arms and legs,
他们杀了一些人，砍断了人们的手臂和双腿
cut off noses, the usual sort of thing,
还有鼻子，诸如此类的
just to show everyone who's who.
就是为了证明他们是谁
And the Nawab gives them his protection?
土邦王保护了他们？
Yes, in return for a share of the loot,
是的，至少我们怀疑交换的条件是
at least that's what we suspect.
分享他们的战利品
He's nothing but a common brigand.
他不过是个普通的强盗
It's just one dash thing after another.
一次又一次的袭击
Ah, but Crawford, that's the definition of our business,
但是克劳福德，这就是我们的机遇
getting out of one dash thing after another.
摆脱一次又一次袭击
What couldn't I give to get out of this one?
我愿意付出一切摆脱这次袭击
Gentlemen.
先生们
What's that singing?
哪儿来的歌声？
It's the entertainment.
是娱乐演出
Oh, do you think it would be all right to go and see?
我过去看看，你觉得可以吗？
Well I suppose so, if you really want to.
如果你真的想去的话，我觉得没问题
These things are supposed to be strictly for men.
这些表演应该是专门为男人准备的
Oh well, go on.
好吧，去吧
Hello.
嗨
Strange music.
奇怪的音乐
- Do you hate it?
你不喜欢吗？
- Heavens no.
天哪，当然不是了
I've just never heard anything like it.
我只是从来没听过这样的音乐
Not a very appreciative audience.
没有一个有鉴赏力的观众
Poor Douglas, he's putting up a great show.
可怜的道格拉斯，你知道，他完全是个乐盲
He's tone deaf you know, utterly.
欣赏不来这场精彩的演出
I have a message for you.
我有个口信给你
Oh yes?
是吗？
As a matter of fact he sent me out to give it to you.
实际上，是他派我出来传口信给你
- But he doesn't even know I exist.
但他都不知道我的存在啊
- Oh doesn't he?
哦，他不知道吗？
He hasn't looked in my direction once, not once all evening.
他整晚都没有往我这个方向看，一次都没有
Well, almost not once anyway, why should he?
好吧，不管怎样，他为什么要往我这个方向看呢？
All the same, he sent me.
他派我出来也是有同样的想法
He wants to invite you and Mr Rivers to dinner next week.
他想邀请你和里弗斯先生下周共进晚餐
Just the two of you, en famille.
只有你们两个
Just Douglas and me?
只有道格拉斯和我吗？
He also wanted me to tell you that it would make him very happy.
他还想让我转告你，他对此非常期待
It would be fun.
会很有趣的
- I have to go.
我得走了
- Oh no.
哦，不行
Please.
求你了
I'll be back in the evening.
我晚上就回来了
In the evening.
要等到晚上啊
Sleep a bit more.
再睡一会儿吧
Douglas?
道格拉斯
Douglas.
I forgot to tell you something.
我忘记告诉你一件事
What's the matter?
怎么了？
Darling, you wouldn't know, I'm not for a moment blaming you,
亲爱的，你不知道吗，现在我真的不想责备你
but you shouldn't let the servants see you like this.
但你不该让仆人看到你这个样子
See me how?
我怎么了？
I'm as demure as a nun, look.
你看，我穿的像个修女一样保守
Oh, this is too ridiculous.
真是太可笑了
What did you want to tell me?
你刚刚要和我说什么？
The Nawab's invited us to dinner on Wednesday.
土邦王邀请我们周三和他共进晚餐
- Oh no, not again.
不会吧，又来一次
- What do you mean "not again"?
你这是什么意思？
It's the only decent place we've been to.
那是唯一一个我们去过的豪华的地方
At least it's amusing.
至少是有趣的
- Amusing? Gosh.
有趣？天啊
- Well, he wants us, anyway.
不管怎样，反正他邀请了我们
He says he'll send a car and everything.
他说他会派车来接我们并安排好一切
But why should he send a car? We can go with the Crawfords.
他为什么要派车接我们呢？我们可以和克劳福德夫妇一起去
Oh, you don't think they've been invited do you?
你不会觉得他们也被邀请了吧？
Well, he wouldn't ask us without the Crawfords.
没有克劳福德夫妇，他不会邀请我们的
I mean Mr Crawford's the burra sahib, he's my superior.
我的意思是，克劳福德先生，是我的上级
He's also a superior bore.
他也是个超级乏味的人
He wants us, darling,
亲爱的，他只邀请了我们
because we're amusing and nice and they're not.
因为我们有趣又平和，不像克劳德福夫妇
- What, just us, just you and me?
为什么只邀请了我们，我和你？
- Well, why not?
为什么不可以呢？
Why it's most irregular.
因为这完全不合常理
Since when does royalty throw parties for junior officers?
什么时候开始皇室为初级职员举办宴会了？
It's very irregular.
完全不合常理
Oh, God.
哦，天哪
I wish you'd trust me on this.
在这件事上，我希望你能相信我
I really do know best, really I do, darling.
因为我是最了解的，我真的非常了解，亲爱的
You don't know.
你根本就不了解
When you're gone, there's nothing, there's nobody.
你上班之后，这里什么都没有，空空荡荡的
My goodness, the days are long.
天哪，每天都过得特别慢
I never knew days could be so long.
我从来没觉得日子会这么慢
I know it's difficult for you, darling,
亲爱的，我知道这一切对你来说很困哪
but it's all just because it's all so new.
但这全都是因为你在一个全新的环境中
As a matter of fact I was talking about this very thing to Beth Crawford.
实际上，我还和贝丝・克劳福德说过这件事
And you mustn't think that way about Beth, she's a good sort.
你千万别生贝丝的气，她是好意
And do you know what she said? She said that, well, someone as sensitive
你知道她说了什么吗？她说像你这样既敏感
and as intelligent as you,
又聪明的人
see she does appreciate you...
看，她是在夸赞你
well, that you'd surely be all right here,
你在这里完全没问题的
but you, and this is what she said,
而你，这也是她说的
that you'd "come to feel about India just as we do".
你对印度的感觉慢慢的会和我们一样
I know it's easy for me, I have my work.
我知道，这对我来说很简单，因为我有工作
I'm really not fit for anything else.
但其他的事情我也不适应
But you're worth a jolly sight more
与其只做我这个家伙的妻子，你值得
than to be just the wife of a chap like me.
更多美好的东西
I should say so.
我应该这么说
I do love you.
我真的很爱你
See you tonight.
晚上见
I may not be here.
我也许不在家
If it gets too boring I'll run away.
如果太无聊了，我就逃走
- I'll play blind.
我要盲打
- Playing blind?
玩儿盲牌？
All right one, two.
好了，一，二
- Yes, you have to show your cards...
是的，你要亮出你的牌
- Show? One.
亮出来吗？
There you are.
这是怎么回事 我赢了
You cheated me.
你骗了我
Honestly, I didn't see your cards.
他肯定作弊了  老实讲，我都没看见你的牌
One, two.
一，二
So this is how you spend your time, you idle fellow...
无聊的家伙，你就是这样打发时间的
- ...playing cards with women?
和女人打牌？
- I'm not playing anymore.
我再也不玩儿了
I've never seen such abdominal cheating.
我从来没见过用肚子作弊的
- You're her own dear son.
你就像是她的亲生儿子
- If I am your own dear son,
如果我是您亲生的儿子
you shouldn't be cheating me like this.
您刚刚就不该那样作弊
Cheating, not I.
作弊？我，没有
- Pay your debts.
快还钱吧
- Come on, Harry, pay up.
快点儿，哈里，把钱都还上
All gentlemen pay their gambling debts.
绅士都会还清自己的赌债
What would they say in the club?
他们会在俱乐部里说什么？
And what would our Mr Crawford say,
我们的克罗弗德先生会说什么
the esteemed burra sahib?
尊敬的
And what about our esteemed sahib, Mr Rivers?
还有我们尊敬的里弗斯先生会说什么？
Oh, here, I've got this courteous note from Mr Rivers.
对了，这是里弗斯先生给我的答谢函
We've left Satipur, all this is his great state of Khatm.
我们已经离开了赛提普，这都是他统治的哈塔姆的领土
Yes, we've left British India.
是的，我们已经离开了英国统治的印度
Now you're in my power, like him.
现在你和他一样都在我的统治下
I'm only joking.
我只是在开玩笑
I had to go with them, I couldn't not.
我不得不和他一起走，我不能拒绝他
He said he'd be so terribly hurt if I didn't,
他说，如果我不来，如果我再一次拒绝他的邀请
if I refused his invitation again.
他会非常的伤心
Look at him, Mrs Rivers.
看看他，里弗斯太太
What sort of an Englishman are you?
你算是什么英国人呢
One who can't stand your goddamn climate.
不能忍受你的这种鬼天气的英国人
My climate?
我的天气？
Well, Mrs Rivers can stand it very well.
里弗斯太太却适应的很好
Oh dear, dear, Mrs Rivers, what shall we do with him?
亲爱的，亲爱的里弗斯太太，我们该拿他怎么办呢？
He's letting down the side.
他真让人失望
That's not a proper Englishman.
不是个像样的英国人
Do you know what I think? I think he's a very improper Englishman.
你知道我在想什么吗？我想他是个非常不像样的英国人
Here.
给
This place is sacred to the memory of Baba Firdaus,
这圣坛是为了纪念巴巴・阿弗道斯
a holy man.
一位虔诚的圣人
It was built in his honour by my ancestor Amanullah Khan.
我的祖先阿曼努汗・坎建此圣坛表示对他的敬意
Oh, the one you told that frightful story about
哦，你讲的那个把所有客人困在帐篷里
who trapped all his guests in a tent and had them stabbed.
并刺杀了所有人的恐怖故事
You... You call that frightful do you?
你觉得很恐怖，是吗？
I suppose you're right.
我想你是对的
Baba Firdaus gave him shelter here after battle.
战后巴巴・阿弗道斯就在此定居
That's why he built this shrine in gratitude.
这也是他把圣坛建在这儿的原因
He never forgot a friend or an enemy.
他从不会忘记一个敌人或者一个朋友
The British liked him very much.
英国人都非常喜欢他
- I think you like such people, don't you?
我觉得你也喜欢这样的人，不是吗？
- We do?
是吗？
Yes, you know, rough people that fight well,
是的，你知道的，粗鲁的人都善战
mostly on a horse, but best of all, you like the horse.
大多时候都在马背上，但最重要的是你喜欢马
But you're not like that. You don't like the horses, do you?
但你不喜欢那样，你不喜欢骑马，对吧？
You're right, I don't.
你说的对，我不喜欢
You see how well I read your character?
你看我多了解你
Thank you, thank you.
谢谢你，谢谢
Well done.
漂亮
Olivia never told Douglas about the Nawab's picnic.
奥莉维亚从来没跟道格拉斯提起和土邦王野餐的事
She had meant to as soon as she got home,
她一回到家，就打算告诉道格拉斯
but it so happened that he'd been held up
但碰巧那天，集市上发生刺杀事件
by a stabbing incident in the bazaar that day
他脱不开身
and was even later than usual.
比平时回来的晚
She never did get around to telling him about her day.
她一直没有机会把那天的事情告诉道格拉斯
And when he left next morning, she was still asleep.
当第二天早上他离开的时候，她还在睡觉
So instead, she wrote the first of those long,
因此，她写下了第一篇非常长的
really intimate letters to Marcia.
秘密信件给玛西亚
Inder Lal's family always comes to the annual religious festival
英德尔・拉尔的家人经常参加在土邦王的祖先，阿曼努汗・坎
at the tomb built by Amanullah Khan, the Nawab's ancestor.
建造的圣坛的一年一度的宗教节日
Amanullah Khan built the shrine for a Muslim saint,
阿曼努汗・坎建此圣坛是为了纪念一位穆斯林圣人
but now it's a sacred place for both Hindus and Muslims.
但现在这个神圣的地方既属于印度教徒也属于穆斯林教徒
That's the way things happen in India, everything gets mixed up and absorbed.
在印度很多事情都是这样的，开始融合并相互吸引
"Shadi", "shadi", meaning marriage,
沙迪，沙迪，是婚姻的意思
that's what they keep asking me.
也是她们一直问我的问题
"Why aren't you married?"
你为什么还不结婚？
"How come you don't have a husband? No children?"
你怎么能没有丈夫和孩子呢？
"How can you live like that?"
你怎么生活呢？
I told them why don't you find someone really nice for me?
我告诉她们，你们为什么不帮我找一个好人呢？
So they asked Maji to provide a candidate.
因此她们请玛姬挑选一个候选人
Maji's a sort of wise woman whom everyone consults about their problems.
玛姬是个聪明的女人，每个人有问题都会请教她
She said "God would provide", which is her usual response.
通常她都会说，上帝会给她指派的
Maji said Lilavati had been coming here
玛姬说，三十年来莉拉瓦蒂
every year, for 30 years.
每年都会来这儿乞讨
Once she'd been a farmer's wife but her husband died
她以前是个农民的妻子，后来丈夫去世
and her in-laws wouldn't keep her
公婆不要她了
so she began to beg for her living.
因此她开始以乞讨为生
She goes round to all the pilgrim spots because that's where people
她去到各种朝圣的地方，因为在那些地方
are most disposed to be charitable.
人们最愿意施舍了
Giving to the poor is one way of accumulating a good record
施舍穷人是一种积德的方式
so as not to have to be born again.
这样就不必经历重生了
This water is incredibly cold.
这里的水非常的凉
It's always like that.
一直都这么凉的
How do you know, have you been here before?
你怎么知道的，你以前来过这里吗？
I read it somewhere. Are you an American?
我在某处读到的，你是美国人吗？
Canadian?
加拿大人？
I'm not anything now.
现在我哪儿人也不是
I've taken sanyas.
我已经接受涅
That means you strip off everything,
也就是说我脱离了一切
your hair, your clothes, all your personal possessions
头发，衣服，所有的私人财产
and your identity.
还有自我
It's all burned up on a funereal pyre.
一切都在火堆里烧掉了
So it's like dying as a material being
就像是生理上死去了
and being reborn spiritually.
精神上重生了
And what about you?
说说你吧
- I'm doing some research.
我在做调研
- What, on your PhD?
什么，你是博士吗？
For myself, like you.
是为了我自己，和你一样
I'm not researching Hinduism, I've become a Hindu.
我不是在调研印度，而是成为了一名印度教徒
Actually, research was what I used to do in England,
实际上，调研是我在英国做的事情
it was my job, I worked with the BBC.
我和BBC合作，那就是我的工作
And you didn't find it all that fulfilling either?
你从中没有找到成就感？
You wouldn't be here if you did.
否则你也不会在这儿了
I gave it ，I gave it all up...
我放弃了，放弃了一切
because it wasn't reality.
因为一切都不是真实的
I even gave up my name.
我甚至放弃了自己的名字
My guru gave me a new one, Chidananda.
我的古鲁领袖给了我一个新名字 奇德阿南达
- Chid.
奇德
- Ananda.
阿南达
- Chidananda.
奇德阿南达
- It means bliss of mind.
代表精神的幸福
But you can just call me Chid.
但你可以叫我奇德
Chid.
奇德
Are you coming in?
你要下来吗？
- Oh it's nice.
真清澈
- Hm, very nice.
非常清澈
You can't have any money or anything, just this.
你不能带钱和任何东西，只有这个
People have to give you food or anything that you need.
人们才会给你食物或者其他你需要的东西
One rupee is good?
一卢比够吗？
Two.
两张票
You've got a lot of room here.
你住的地方房间挺多
Just for a couple of days, for a little rest.
我就在这儿停留几天，休息一下
All right, all right, but just two days.
好吧，好吧，就两天
I'll show you where.
我带你去你住的地方
Nice.
舒服
It's the light around our body that controls our mind.
我们身体周围的光控制着我们的思想
A pure unharmful mind is a place of perfect happiness.
拥有纯洁善良的思想就得到了真正的幸福
- Light.
光？
- Light?
Whoa, all right come over.
好了，快过来
No, no, no, no.
不，不，不
By the way, when are you leaving?
对了，你打算什么时候离开？
They want me to stay.
他们希望我留下来
Do you even know how poor these people are?
你知道这些人有多穷吗？
They can't afford to feed you.
他们养不起你的
They like it, they like giving.
他们喜欢这样了，喜欢给予
By giving they're taking good karma for their next reincarnation.
今生施舍给予，来生才能结善缘
So you're helping them to a better time in the next life
这么说你在这儿白吃白喝是帮助他们
by eating their food in this one?
来世投个好胎？
I used to be just like you, once.
我以前就和你一样
I wanted materialistic power.
我想要物质上的满足
I was fascinated with power.
我完全沉迷于这种满足感
I went to the library and got all these books
我去图书馆读了很多
on Julius Caesar and Octavius Augustus, those sort of people.
关于奥古斯都・凯撒和盖乌斯・屋大维这类人的书籍
I figured that today's equivalent is big business,
我发现体现在当今社会的等价物就是
big multinational corporations.
跨国集团的大生意
You know I tried to get in on an IBM training course one time,
你知道吗，有一次我曾经参加一场美国国际商用机器公司的培训
but my grades weren't good enough,
但我的成绩不够优秀
and they said that I was crazy,
他们说我疯了
and they sent me to the hospital.
把我送进了医院
That's a tazkiyah procession.
这是游行队伍
It took me a long time to realise that what the Romans had was limited power
我花了很长时间才意识到罗马人拥有的是有限的满足
and that the only unlimited power is what they had in the Vedanta.
而唯一不受限的满足就是不断和精神世界融合
You see, materialistic power is limited.
你要明白物质上的满足是有限的
Real power is absolute, unlimited and undefined.
真正的满足是完全不受限且不明确的
You see, you must be independent in your thinking.
你知道的，你必须要独立思考
But back home they're afraid of that.
但回到现实，他们对此很害怕
Afraid that you might overthrow their power structure.
害怕你推翻他们的满足体系
So they say you're crazy...
所以他们才会说你疯了
put you in a hospital.
把你送进医院
What are you doing？
你在做什么？
I'm just looking.  Drop those things .  there's no harm in looking.
我只是看一下  快放下      看看又不会怎么样
You shouldn't be looking through other people's things like that.
你不应该这样翻看别人的信件
- Absolutely.
当然
- Just throw it all out.
把它们都扔掉
I'll throw you out!
我要把你扔出去
If I ever catch you going through my things again
如果我再抓到你翻看我的东西
I'll throw you out, beads and bangles, begging bowl and all.
我就把你扔出去，你的念珠，手镯，化缘钵，所有的东西都扔出去
Let go of me.
放开我
You know I'm surprised at you.
你知道吗，我还挺惊讶的
I wasn't going through your papers, I was looking for money.
我没打算偷看你的信件，我是在找钱
- Money, what do you need money for?
钱？你要钱做什么？
- Well, you want me to go.
你不是想让我离开吗？不是吗？
You live free, you eat free, you beg in the streets.
你吃住都不需要钱，你还上街乞讨
Don't touch.
不许碰
I know what you think.
我知道你怎么想的
You think you're Olivia, her reincarnation.
你认为你就是奥莉维亚，她的来世
You've seen the photos of her. How could I ever be her?
你看过她的照片了，我怎么可能是她呢？
Anyway, where would I ever find a Nawab
不管怎样，如果我需要一个土邦王
even if I needed one, I mean if I wanted one.
我要去哪儿找呢？我是说当我真的需要的时候
I know what you need, you need sex.
我知道你需要什么，你需要性爱
You mean you do.
你是说你需要吧
Why don't you get out of here?
你为什么不离开这里？
I can't help it.
我也情不自禁
It gets to this enormous size, do you want to see?
它就变得这么大了，你想看看吗？
No, I don't.
不，不想
It's due to the mediation, I mean that's a fact,
这是因为冥想的原因，但这是事实
I get charged up with this terrific voltage.
我被你曼妙的身材吸引力
No, don't laugh, it's a liability.
不，不要笑，你要对我负责
Now come on, Anne.
来吧，安妮
Ow, ow.
喔，喔
Psst.
嘘
Psst, Anne, Anne?
嘘，安妮，安妮？
You're cutting yourself off from the real love experience.
你在切断自己与真爱之间的联系
It's not just sex, it's a union with all life.
这不仅仅是性，这是所有生命的结合
The sexual drive is towards the ultimate orgasm.
性冲动是导向终极高潮的
That ultimate union rising up through the chakras
通过脉轮导向终极纽带
to the third eye, the pineal gland.
导向第三只眼睛，松果体
Explosion of light at the top of the skull.
在头顶形成光
An out of sight, spaced out, super consciousness.
超越视线，魂飞天外，醍醐灌顶
Jesus Christ.
上帝啊
You've got to get in touch with your own femininity, Anne.
你必须激发你自己的女性气质
With your own inner space.
拥有自己的内心世界
What do you think about me taking her to a doctor
你觉得我带她看医生
who specialises in this sort of thing?
治疗这种病的专家，怎么样？
You only get well if you believe in something, Anne.
阿妮，拥有信仰一切才会变好
What do you mean like that, what's going on in there?
你这话是什么意思，里面是怎么回事？
Laugh at us if you wish.
你想嘲笑我们的话，请随便
Oh, no, no, I wouldn't laugh at you. I mean how can, why should I?
哦，不，不，我没有嘲笑你，我的意思是，我怎么会，为什么会嘲笑你们呢？
It's just I think it's worth trying a different form of treatment.
我只是觉得尝试一种不同的治疗方式也未尝不可
I think I should take her to Delhi.
我觉得我应该带她去德里
- There must be doctors there who...
那里一定有医生
- You mean a psychiatrist?
你是说精神病医生吗？
- Who asked you?
谁问你了？
- Don't listen to her.
不要听她的
Psychiatrists are gross.
精神病医生都是庸医
Stay out of this, I'm talking to Inder Lal.
你别插嘴，我在和英德尔・拉尔说话
I'm telling you, I know.
我告诉你，我最了解
Let's just try, I mean I'll...
咱们就去试一试，我的意思是我会……
I think it's just worth trying, me taking her there.
我觉得让我带她去德里试一试是很值得的
Look there's no need, we've made other arrangements.
听我说，不必了，我们已经做了其他的安排
Have you, what sort of arrangements?
是吗？什么安排？
Well, we're going to a pilgrimage to Amarnath.
我们要去阿玛尔纳特朝拜
Mother wants to go.
妈妈想去
- A pilgrimage?
去朝拜？
- Yeah.
是的
But what... Oh gosh, oh dear.
可是，天哪，天哪
They all say this must be done and if I say no they will blame me for it.
他们都同意去朝拜，如果我不同意，他们会因此责怪我的
Look do give him something. And then there's this man behind.
听我说，给他一些东西吧，还有后面的这个人
Please give him something.
请给他一些东西吧
You know, some yogis can actually take their intestines out
你知道吗，一些瑜伽信徒真的会把他们的肠子拿出来
wash them, clean them and put them back in, all nice and clean.
清洗，清洗干净后再完好无损地放回去
How disgusting.
真恶心
I've never seen anyone like you for telling other people
我从来没见过像你这样的人，告诉别人
that their ideas and philosophies are disgusting.
他们的思想和信仰是恶心的
What good are philosophies and ideas when someone's sick?
当人生病的时候，思想和信仰有什么用呢？
All they can come up with to help her is to take her on a pilgrimage.
他们能想出来的帮她的办法就是带她去朝圣
That's right, and I'm going to.
对，我也会去
We're going up to Amarnath to see the Shiva Lingam.
我们要爬上阿玛尔纳特看辛格里诺
Other nostril.
另外一个鼻孔
What's that, Shiva's prick?
那是什么？希瓦的咒锥吗？
Yeah something like that.
是的，差不多吧
It's an object of Hindu worship for women from the day they are born.
从女人出生的那天开始，印度教徒朝奉女人的圣物
Now breathe.
现在深呼吸
It's eight feet tall.
它有八英尺高
You should come with us, Anne.
安妮，你应该和我们一起去
It's more than 50 years ago,
尽管是五十多年前
but I'll never forget the dust storms we had that year.
但我绝不会忘记那一年我们遭遇的沙尘暴
They blew all day, they blew all night.
日夜不停地吹
If you left a chink open anywhere
假如你在某个地方留了一个缝隙
within seconds there would be a fume of dust over everything.
所有的东西马上就盖上了一层灰尘
It got in your eyes, your nostrils,
你的眼睛，你的鼻孔
it was gritty between your teeth.
你的牙缝里都会有沙尘
Once those dust storms started, they seemed to go on forever.
这些沙尘暴一旦开始就好像再也不会停下一样
No, no, please, I wouldn't like to disturb you.
不，不，请别关，我不想打扰到你
Oh, that's all right.
哦，没关系的
Have you had a letter?
你收到了一封信？
Yes, I had this letter from Mother.
是的，我妈妈的来信
They got as far as Palghat.
他们已经到了巴尔卡德了
- Oh, that's a good, isn't it?
他们还挺快的
- They send you greetings.
他们向你问好
See it says...
看，上面写着
Hot winds whistled and columns of dust
热风呼啸，沙漠里的沙尘
came blowing in from the desert.
不断来袭
No wonder everyone went mad.
毫无疑问，所有人都失去了理智
I gave up.
我放弃了
I simply lay in bed, too lethargic to do a thing.
只好躺在床上，提不起精神做任何事
And I was a young man then, mind you.
请注意，当时我还是个年轻人
But then it was decided we were to go to the mountains,
但后来我们决定去爬山
into the cool air, not to Simla,
去一个凉爽的地方，但不是西米拉
where all the official British types went, but to Masuri, where the Nawab had a house.
一个英国官员都去的地方。是马苏里，土邦王在那儿有一套房子
Well, we all packed up and there was great excitement
我们都准备好行李，非常地兴奋
and relief and I can tell you we could hardly wait to get up there.
有种解放了的感觉，我可以告诉你，我们迫不及待想去那里
Then the begum heard an owl.
可是女王听见猫头鹰叫
Or at least I think it was an owl.
反正我觉得是猫头鹰
Anyway, it was something inauspicious,
无所谓了，这是不详的征兆
a warning that we must on no accounts set out on a journey.
警告我们决不能踏上这场旅途
The Nawab was very restless, excited,
土邦王当时非常焦躁，兴奋
never sat still for a minute.
坐立不安
He was very short tempered with all of us.
还经常对我们发脾气
I couldn't help remembering what I'd heard,
我突然想起来我听到的
about how he was in league with Tikaram's gang.
他是如何和普兰达那群强盗结盟的
Tikaram was a dacoit
普兰达是一个强盗
with a price of 10,000 rupees on his head.
他的头颅价值一万卢比
He and his gang went all around the countryside
他和他的团伙在乡下四处抢劫
looting people and killing anyone who got in their way,
并杀害阻止他们的人
or even just for the fun of it.
甚至只是为了好玩儿
They could do all this with impunity
他们的所作所为不收制约
because they enjoyed the Nawab's protection.
因为他们享有土邦王的保护特权
At least, that's what the British said.
至少英国方面是这么说的
They said he took a share in their loot and used them as his henchmen
他们说土邦王和强盗们分享战利品，并把他们当成自己的亲信
and if anyone informed on them
如果有人举报他们
they would take their revenge on a whole village.
他们会报复整个村庄
If something really horrible happened...
如果非常严重的事情发生了
don't you think I ought to... help you bear it?
你觉得我不应该帮你分担吗？
It all started in a...
这一切发生在
in a house in Chota bazaar.
卓塔集市的一间屋子里
Two women quarrelling over a bucket of water.
两个女人因为一桶水吵了起来
But in this season, with the heat coming on, things grow and build up
但在这个季节，炎热的天气就要来了，万物复苏，繁荣生长
and before you know where you are, you have a full scale riot on your hands
当你意识到你身处何地时，你接手了一场大规模的骚乱
and then there's no holding anyone.
却没抓到任何人
They were throwing acid today.
今天他们互相泼酸
They were aiming for the face, eyes.
泼向对方的脸，眼睛
The screams.
那些惨叫声
I'll never forget those screams.
我永远都忘不了那些惨叫声
- Superintendent, one round only.
指挥官，只来一轮
- Take aim.
瞄准
Fire.
开火
The British also suspected the Nawab
英国人还怀疑土邦王
of using the dacoits to help inflame riots against them
利用盗贼的势力帮助暴徒反抗他们
like the one outside the Satipur Jail in,
比如赛提普监狱外的那场暴乱
I think it was 1923.
我记得是1923年
Anyway, Crawford was away on tour and Douglas was in charge
不管怎样，克劳福德出去游玩了，道格拉斯主事
and had to arrest the ringleaders of what had been a very ugly massacre.
而且不得不抓捕导致这场血流成河的大屠杀的暴徒首领
Well, when all these kinds of things happened
当这一切发生的时候
I just gave up and ran away to Olivia's house
我只好放弃，逃到奥莉维亚的家里
and begged her to play some Schumann.
请她弹奏一些舒曼的曲子
Lovely.
好听
真好听
You don't mind if Harry stays with us for a day or two, do you?
你不介意哈里在我们家住一两天吧？
What?
什么？
Oh, no.
哦，不介意
No, no, I want him to.
我希望他留在这儿
It's better for him to be here than there.
他在这儿总比皇宫好
Bra vissima.
太棒了
Oh, what fun.
真有意思
You do know Mr Hamilton-Paul, don't you, Beth?
贝丝，你认识汉密尔顿先生，对吧？
I most certainly do, we've met oh so many times at the palace.
当然认识了，我们在皇宫的时候碰到过很多次
He's come to stay with us for a while.
他来我们家住一段时间
Oh, I'm so glad that you're not alone at this time.
我非常开心，你现在不会感到孤单了
Not that there's anything whatsoever to worry about Olivia.
奥莉维亚，你也没什么可担心的了
That's what I came here to speak to you about.
这也是我要和你说的
And Arthur is back and he and Douglas have the situation absolutely in hand.
亚瑟回来了，他和道格拉斯完全展控了现在的形式
- What situation?
什么形势？
- Oh you know, the usual.
你知道的，和平常一样
You mustn't think about.
你别多想
Now what I really want you to think about is Simla.
现在我希望你认真考虑的是西米拉
No dear I'm not nagging at you, but we really all do feel...
亲爱的，我没有，没有唠叨你，但我们都觉得
It's true Olivia, you shouldn't be here through the summer, it's unbearable.
奥莉维亚，你真的不该整个夏天都待在这里，这里酷热不堪
- But if you can bear it?
但既然你能忍受？
- Who said I could?
谁说我可以了？
One summer we did manage to get up to Masuri.
有一个夏天，我们的确去了马苏里避暑
The Nawab has a marvellous house up there,
土邦王有一所非常豪华的房子在那儿
it's a swish chalet with a dash of gothic cathedral.
瑞士小木屋，还有哥特式的教堂
Very impressive indeed.
让人印象非常深刻
Not that I got much time to enjoy it.
可我当时没有太多的时间享受
A dead bat was found in all of places the begum's bedroom
因为女王的卧室里发现了一只死蝙蝠
so we had to pack up and come back home immediately.
所以我们不得不立刻收拾行李回家
Actually, this year I wasn't thinking so much
实际上，今年我想回家
of going to the mountains as of going home.
并没有考虑去山里避暑
You see I'm worried about my mother,
你懂的，我母亲最近身体不太好
she hasn't been too well and...
我很担心她
Well, of course you must go.
那你当然要回去了
And do you know the Ross-Milbanks?
你认识罗斯・米尔班克吗？
He's been the DC over at Cawnpore.
他一直是坎普尔的首脑
They're on home leave now driving down to Bombay
他们要休假回家，正开车去孟买
to catch the P&O
赶P&O火车
But those P&O aren't they always booked up,
但P&O的车票经常订满
completely booked, months ahead?
不是要提前几个月预定吗？
Oh, but a single berth.
哦，但只是一张单人票而已
And we could always send a cable to the Gibbons in Bombay.
我们总是可以给孟买的吉本斯发电报
- Really?
真的吗？
- Really and truly.
真的，千真万确
Mr Gandhi's lot probably stirring things up again.
甘地先生可能又在挑起事端了
They never miss a chance.
他们不放过任何一次机会
No, don't bother to get up.
不用了，别劳神起身了
Where are Mr and Mrs Rivers?
里佛斯夫妇在哪儿？
They've gone to church and then I think they're going to the club.
他们去教堂了，接着我想他们会去俱乐部
Oh, what's here?
这都是什么？
Tea, toast and marmalade, boiled eggs three minutes,
茶，烤面包，果酱，煮了三分钟的鸡蛋
an English newspaper.
一份英国报纸
Four months old but yes it's English.
四个月前的了，不过确实是英国报纸
Well, I can see you have thoroughly deserted us.
在我看来，你是已经彻底抛弃我们了
My poor mother and all the ladies keep asking,
我可怜的母亲，还有王妃们不停地问我
"Where is Harry, when is he coming home?"
哈里去哪儿了？什么时候回家？
I answer he is home, he's with his own people whom he loves.
我回答他们，他在家里呢，和他喜欢的人一起生活
Isn't that true?
我说的不对吗？
Now you see, you don't say anything.
看看，现在你又一言不发
You don't give one a chance to say anything.
是你不给我说话的机会
I know I'm a monster egoist,
我知道我是一个以自我为中心的魔鬼
or a plain monster.
或者纯粹是个魔鬼
But my goodness for a monster,
但作为魔鬼，我也有慈悲之心
I do grow fond of other people
我会渐渐地喜欢上别人
and miss them when they leave me.
当他们离开的时候，还会想念他们
Now what's the matter?
你又怎么了？
- I can just see you missing me.
我只是知道了你想我
- Oh no, of course not.
不，不，当然不是了
I'm here for the sole purpose of leaving my calling card
我来这儿只有一个目的，把我的召见卡
on Mr and Mrs Rivers.
给里弗斯夫妇
Don't be a fool, Harry.
别犯傻了，哈里
You know why I'm here.
你知道我来这里的原因
- See you later, old man.
稍后见，老兄
- Bravo.
稍后见
Oh, Olivia, do tell Mr Hamilton-Paul
奥莉维亚，请转告汉密尔顿保罗
that the Milbanks are getting here on Tuesday
米尔班克周二到
and could take him with them to Bombay.
可以带他一起去孟买
- We have a berth for him.
我们给他买了一张车票
- Good work, Beth.
贝丝，太好了
But darling, Harry's the Nawab's guest.
可是，亲爱的，哈里是土邦王的客人
He can't just run out on him at a moment's notice with Mrs Crawford...
他不能因为克劳德福太太的一句话就抛弃他
- Morning.
早上好
- ...Mrs Crawford's friends.
还是克劳福德太太的朋友
- I can't see what's wrong with that.
我不觉得有什么问题
But the Nawab paid his fare
但是土邦王支付了他的车费
and he's been keeping him, hasn't he, in the lap of luxury for some time?
这段时间一直让他养尊处优，不是吗？
He shouldn't be there in the first place.
他一开始就不应该住在那里
No Englishman has any business living in that palace.
英国人不该和那座皇室扯上关系
Don't be so stuffy.
别这么古板
I'm sorry.
对不起
Those are my feelings and I must be allowed to express them.
这都是我的感受，我有权表达出来
I could do without this particular Sunday caller.
要是没有这个特别的周日召见就好了
I'm delighted to see you.
很高兴见到你
Mrs Rivers, what a charming dress.
里弗斯太太，你的裙子真漂亮
And Mr Rivers, I'm more than delighted to congratulate you on your handling
里弗斯先生，我无比荣幸地恭喜你解决了
the Chota bazaar incident. You were most prompt.
卓塔集市的袭击  你是最果断的
I wish I'd been prompt enough to get there
我希望我的果断是在袭击发生之前
before rather than after the event.
而不是袭击之后
Oh, Mr Rivers, what can be done?
哦，里弗斯先生，还能做些什么呢？
These people will never learn.
民众从来不吸取教训
As to your conduct in this miserable affair there's nothing but praise.
至于你在这次暴乱中的表现，让人十分钦佩
You are misinformed.
您理解错了
It sparked off a lot of resentment.
这次暴乱产生了很多怨恨
You must've heard of all the troubles outside the jail and other places.
您一定听说了，监狱和其他宫廷外的冲突
They get hot and then they cool off.
他们一会儿发起暴乱，过会儿就停止了
It's like our weather and its season.
就像这里的季节和天气一样
Please get dressed, we must go.
请换好衣服，我们该走了
Oh, Mrs Crawford asked us to tell you that the Milbanks
对了，克劳福德太太要我们转告你，米尔班克
are arriving on Tuesday and they're expecting you to go with them.
周二就到了，希望你和他们一起走
Oh, to Bombay?  Yes, Harry told me about it.
去孟买吗？是的，哈里和我说了
Please get dressed, my dear fellow.
我亲爱的朋友，请换好衣服
I hope you don't expect me to take you home in this state.
你不希望我把这个装扮的你带回家吧？
Mrs Crawford says that they have booked a berth for you.
克劳福德太太还说，他们给你订了一张车票
There's been a misunderstanding. I shall apologise to Mrs Crawford myself
这其中一定是有误会，我会亲自向克劳德福太太致歉的
and thank her for her kind efforts on behalf of my guest.
并谢谢她对我的客人友好的帮助
But you wanted to go, your mother is ill.
可是你想回去，你妈妈病了
We must be thankful.
我们十分欣慰
Mother is better.
妈妈有所好转了
And my mother has written to her to invite her to the palace.
我妈妈已经写信给她，邀请她来王宫
She has written, I translate from Urdu,
她已经写完了，我做的翻译
"You now have not one son but two..."
您现在不是有一个儿子，而是两个
"...and both your sons are eager for your visit."
而您的两个儿子都期待您的到来
Thanks awfully for having me.
非常感谢你们收留我
It's true, you know, I do want to go back to the palace.
你知道的，我是真的想回到皇宫去
We talked it over before you came.
你们回来之前我们就说过了
I do want to.
我确实想回去
You don't have to.
你可以不回去的
I want to.
可我想回去
Please get dressed, come on.
赶紧去换衣服吧，快去吧
Look at you, is this the way to appear in front of a lady?
看看你自己，要这个样子出现在一位女士面前吗？
You know, he doesn't know what he wants.
你知道，他并不清楚自己想要什么
One day it's this, one day it's that.
今天这样，明天那样
What can I do?
我能怎么办呢？
I've grown fond of him, he's my friend.
他是我的朋友，我越来越喜欢他了
And once I love a friend it's for life, forever.
而且一旦我喜欢一个朋友，都是我一辈子的朋友
Whatever faults he may have.
不管他犯了什么错
I'd love to read some Trollope or Dickens.
我喜欢特罗洛普或狄更斯的书
Lot's of cold, damp, foggy London scenes,
很多寒冷潮湿，雾气蒙蒙的伦敦景色
that's what I'm longing for.
是我一直向往的
Oh, come away, they're all pornographic.
走开，那都是色情小说
It's a princess being got ready for her nuptial night.
一位公主为她的新婚夜做好了准备
They're doing all sorts of intimate things to her.
他们对她做了各种亲密的事情
Come away.
别看了
Harry, what is all this about dacoits?
哈里，这些强盗究竟是怎么回事？
Honestly I don't know, Olivia.
奥莉维亚，说实话，我也不知道
A lot of things go on and, quite frankly, I'd just as soon not know about them.
发生了很多事，老实讲，我可能很快就不记得了
Gosh I feel I awful.
天啊，我感觉糟透了
But Harry, doesn't he ever talk to you about...
可是哈里，他从来没和你讲过……
I hope I'm not disturbing, please say if I am and I'll run away at once.
希望我没有打扰到你们，如果有的话，请告诉我，我马上离开
How very kind of you to come and see our poor patient.
你真的太善良了，来探望我们可怜的病人
How do you find him? I've sent for Dr Puri.
你是怎么找到他的？我已经派人去接普伦医生了
He's a witch doctor, please don't bring him near me.
他是个巫医，请不要让他靠近我
Don't be ridiculous.
别耍性子了
We want you to get well again quickly.
我们希望你迅速的好起来
We miss you. It's very boring without you, isn't it, Olivia?
我们都想你，没有你太无聊了，对吗，奥莉维亚？
She's been asking about the dacoits.
她一直在问强盗的事情
I hope if there's something you want to know
我希望，你如果想知道什么事情的话
you'll ask me,
直接问我，除了我以外
not Harry or anybody else, but me.
不要问哈里或者其他人
What have you heard?
你听说了什么？
What are they saying?
他们是怎么说的？
You must tell me,
你一定要告诉我
you must give me a chance to defend myself against these slanders.
你必须给我一个为自己辩解的机会
What on Earth are you asking her to do?
你到底让她做什么了？
Bring you reports from the Civil Lines at Satipur?
帮你偷赛提普白城的报告吗？
Do you want her to be your spy?
你让她当你的间谍吗？
- I hope you don't think that of me.
我希望你不是这么看我的
- Of course I don't.
我当然没有
I wouldn't for a minute.
一刻也没有
How could you think it?
你怎么能这么想呢？
No, no, I don't.
不，不，我没有
I know you understand me.
我知道你理解我
That's why I trust you.
这也是我相信你的原因
- What did they want?
他们想要什么？
- Protection.
保护
It seems that the same gang who raided that village
好像袭击那个村庄的那群强盗
are now threatening the local traders.
现在在威胁当地的商人
Trying to extort money for themselves and their chief.
为他们自己和首领敲诈更多的钱财
Who's their chief?
他们的首领是谁？
Well, we suspect our friend.
我们怀疑是我们的朋友
Do you mean the Nawab?
你是说土邦王吗？
But he's a ruler, he wouldn't get mixed up with a robber gang.
他是个统治者，才不会和一群盗贼同流合污呢
After all, he's a prince.
毕竟，他是个王子
Yes, and he's bankrupt,
是的，加上他破产了
having bled his unfortunate subject's wife
他那个不幸的第一任妻子或多或少地
by means of more or less legitimate extortion.
通过法律手段瓜分了他的财产
He's now taken to cruder methods.
虽然听起来很不舒服
Not to put too fine a point on it to outright robbery.
但他已经采取粗暴的方式直接抢劫
I don't believe a word of it.
我一点儿也不相信
Must you smoke that dashed thing...
这么热的天，你一定要抽
in this heat?
那个破玩儿意吗？
You should've gone to Simla.
你应该去西米拉的
And do what, go for walks with Beth Crawford?
去做什么？和贝丝・克劳福德一起散步吗？
Go to the same old boring old dinner parties.
反复参加那些古板无聊的晚宴吗？
One more of those and I shall lie down and die.
你再提一次，我就躺下等死
I don't know what's the matter with me.
我不知道我是怎么了
Why I get so worked up over every little thing.
为什么总是因为一点儿小事就发脾气呢？
I told you, it's the heat.
我告诉你了，是天气热的原因
No Englishwoman is supposed to stand this weather.
没有一个英国女人可以忍受这种炎热的天气
You have these set notions
你已经给英国女人
about what English women are supposed to stand.
能忍受什么设立了标准
Why should anyone tell me what I can stand
为什么每个人都告诉我，我能忍受什么
and what I can't stand?
我不能忍受什么呢？
If you really want to know
如果你真的想知道
the one thing I can't stand is English women.
我不能忍受的一件事，那就是英国女人
Memsahibs.
小姐们
But the rest...
至于其他的
I'm so happy here, I never want to go away.
我在这儿非常开心，从没想过要离开
I wish you would tell Dr Saunders to go and see Harry
我希望你让桑德斯医生去看看哈里
at the palace, he just isn't getting any better.
在王宫里，他一点儿都没有好转
Well...
好的
Dr Saunders doesn't really see private patients
桑德斯医生不怎么看私人病人
unless it's one of us.
除非是我们中的一个
Isn't in Harry one of us？
哈里不是我们中的一员吗？
And if not, am I one of us, do you think?
假如他不是，你认为我是吗？
It might even be that I love you because you're not.
也许正因为你不是，我才爱你
You know sometimes I wish I could afford some feelings,
你知道，有时候我希望自己能释放一些情绪
because I get hot too, I get angry, I want to lose my temper, but...
因为我也热，我也愤怒，我也想发脾气，但是
there are always people watching everywhere.
到处都有人在监视
One simply cannot.
我就是不能
Not even for a minute.
甚至一分钟也不能
It's a bore I know.
我知道这很无聊
When we have a baby, I want him to be just like you.
等我们有了孩子，我要他像你一样
No, no, like you.
不，不，要像你
Like Olivia.
像奥莉维亚
Oh, Olivia's no good.
哦，奥莉维亚不好
Oh, don't say that.
哦，别这么说
Oh, it's all out of tune.
哦，全都不在调上
There's no one to play it.
这里没人会弹钢琴
I'd ordered it for my wife.
这是我为我妻子定制的
- Did she play?
她弹过吗？
- She was keen to learn...
她认真的学习过
but by the time the piano arrived, she had left.
可是这架钢琴送到的时候，她已经离开了
I suppose you know about my marriage?
我猜你已经知道我的婚姻状况了？
I've heard.
我听说过
Oh yes, of course you must've heard a lot of things.
当然了，你一定听说了很多事
There are always people to spread lies about me,
人们总是到处散播我的谣言
including my wife's family.
包括我妻子的娘家
She was much too young for me, Olivia.
她比我小太多了，奥莉维亚
I loved her, as one loves a child.
我爱她就像爱一个孩子一样
Not as I would love a woman.
不是爱一个女人
What a pity.
真可惜
You know, I know what happened, more or less.
你知道的，我或多或少意识到有什么事发生了
After all, it's quite easy to find out
what a person did, but...
毕竟，很容易就能发现一个人做了什么，但是
what made them do it.
什么促使他们那样做了呢
I don't know.
我不知道
I was thinking how India changes people.
我在想印度是如何改变人们的
Just in subtle ways.
潜移默化中就改变了
Just by being here.
站在这里就足够了
I feel you have changed.
我觉得你变了
But you're still too much in your head, not in your heart.
可你脑袋里还是装了太多东西，心里却没与
I suppose so.
也许是吧
Oh, but I admire you.
但我很欣赏你
You're so...
你太
philosophical.
你太理智了
I don't want to be philosophical.
我不想变得理智
Oh, what do you want to be then?
那你想变成什么样？
I don't know, like other people.
不知道，和其他人一样吧
You know when you talk like that to me,
你知道吗，当你和我讲那些话的时候
I don't always unders...
我不总是
I don't always understand you.
我不总是能理解你
But when we are together like this,
担当我们像现在这样在一起的时候
I feel you are my very great friend.
我觉得你是我非常好的朋友
I am your very great friend.
我就是你非常好的朋友
Hello.
嗨
Were you waiting for me?
你是在等我吗？
I hoped you were.
我希望你在等我
You must excuse me, Rivers, but these people are enough
里弗斯，你务必原谅我，但这些人
to drive anyone out of their mind.
谁都忍受不了
They bring me some woman pretending she's miscarrying
他们带来一些女人，假装流产了
and when I curette her I discover...
当我用刮匙检查的时候发现
it's always the same, they've aborted her.
他们给这些女人堕胎的方法一模一样
They stick this twig into her and do it with that.
把这个树枝插进女人的身体里帮她们堕胎
Abortion, mind you, it's a criminal act.
我要提醒你，堕胎是违法的
And then they try to fool me.
他们居然想骗我
I'm sorry you had to come in on this, Rivers, what can I do for you?
里佛斯，很抱歉让你听我发牢骚，你找我有什么事吗？
I wanted to ask you a particular favour.
我有个不情之请
You know Harry Hamilton-Paul who's staying at the palace?
你认识皇宫里那个哈里・汉密尔顿保罗吗？
Oh yes, yeah, him.
哦，哈里，认识
He's not very well and Olivia and I thought that it'd...
他身体不太好，我和奥莉维亚想
Well.
好吧
I wonder what he's been eating over there.
我想知道他在皇宫里一直吃什么
You see it's question of diet, Nawab Sahib.
土邦王陛下，这是饮食习惯的问题
I've seen hundreds of cases like this, thousands.
我见过成百上千个这样的病人
Did you know that most Indians suffer from amoebic dysentery, it's a fact.
你知道大多数印度人都患有阿米巴痢疾吗？这是事实
- Is that true? How interesting.
真的吗？那太有意思了
- They try and cheat you.
他们想方设法地骗你
When I say, "What did you eat?"
当我问，你吃了什么？
They'll say, "Only what you said Dr Sahib,"
他们回答，萨希卜医生，都是听从您的要求
but of course they can't fool me.
但事实上，他们骗不了我
"Oh yes, and what about those chilies, hmm?"
是吗？那这些辣椒是怎么回事？
"And that curry you've had? What, you liar, you cheat?"
这就是你所谓的咖喱吗？简直是睁眼说瞎话
Sometimes I don't waste any time.
有时候我不会浪费时间
I smartly box their ears, one, two, one, two.
直接给他们几个耳光，一二，一二
- It's the only language they understand.
这是他们唯一能听懂的两个词
- You're absolutely right, Dr Saunders.
桑德斯医生，你说的很对
Well, it's no use arguing with them. They're not amenable to reason.
跟他们争论也没用，他们不懂得推理
They haven't got it here you see, up here, the way we have.
他们不会像我们这样用脑，思考问题
He really is exceptionally obnoxious.
他真的非常招人讨厌
- Please don't judge us by him.
请不要用他来评判我们
- Who's us?
我们是谁？
I don't know how you feel about it, but don't lump me in with that lot.
我不知道你是怎么想的，但请不要把我和他们混为一谈
Harry, you can't say the Crawfords are like Dr Saunders,
哈里，你不会认为克劳福德夫妇像桑德斯医生
or the Minnies, or for that matter, Douglas.
或明尼夫妇一样吧，又或者是道格拉斯
And you?
那你呢？
They're all the same.
他们都是一类人
So you do lump me in with them.
所以你确实认为我和他们一样
You, I wouldn't for a minute, not for a minute think of you,
你，我一刻也没有，一刻也没有这么想
speak of you in the same breath.
同时也没有批判你
To me, you're better, beautiful, wonderful,
对我来说，你，美丽大方善良
more wonderful, absolutely terrific.
你是最美丽的，非常完美
- Is that what you wanted to hear?
这是你想听的吗？
- Harry, Olivia, look, I mean,
哈里，奥莉维亚，你们听我说
instead of having a rotten time let's have some fun.
与其在这儿虚度时光，不如找点儿乐子
Let me tell you a dream, my dream, my latest dream, you know.
我和你们讲一个梦，一个我的梦，我最近做的梦，你们知道吗
I dreamt of Mrs Crawford.
我梦见了克劳福德太太
- You dream about Mrs Crawford?
你梦见了克劳福德太太？
- Not the way you mean, I mean,
不是你想的那样，我的意思是
Mrs Crawford was not Mrs Crawford.
克劳福德太太，不是克劳福德太太
- She was a hijra.
她是个宦官
- What's a hijra?
宦官是什么？
Oh my poor Olivia, you don't know?
哦，我的傻奥莉维亚，你不知道吗？
We must educate her.
看来我们要教教她
At first, she couldn't work out
一开始，她不知道
that these were men, eunuchs.
那些宦官是男人
- Hijra?
宦官？
- Yes.
是的
It was all so strange and wonderfully exotic
在充满异国风情的奇妙世界里
and she forgot everything, joined in the fun.
她抛开一切享受其中的快乐
Forgot herself, you might say.
可以说达到忘我的境界
I kept trying to warn her but she wouldn't listen.
我一直试着提醒她，但她不听
You see, she was outraging two conventions,
你知道的，她违背了双方的约定
those of her own people and those of the Indians,
一方是她自己的国家，一方的印度
whose conventions are, if anything, even stronger
如果发生什么事，就看哪一方更强大了
and of course you can't do anything in India
当然在印度，你的一举一动
without everyone knowing about it,
家喻户晓
the servants see to that.
仆人们会看着办的
You know, there's a story about that old woman
你听过一个老女人
in the purdah quarters.
在营房的故事吗？
How she killed off an unwanted bride
她给婚纱染上毒药水
by dressing her up in poisoned wedding gowns.
毒死了一位不受欢迎的新娘
What?
什么？
Apparently it's true.
千真万确
They dipped the cloth into poison
他们把婚纱浸泡在毒水里
and then when you put it on it clings to you.
当你穿上婚纱的时候，你就中毒了
Frightful.
真可怕
Oh, there are all sorts of stories about what goes on in the purdah quarters.
营房里流传着各种各样的故事
Secret arts, magic potions and all the rest of it.
邪术，魔法药水，应有尽有
Oh, come on now, those old things in there?
不会吧，现在还有这种古老的方法？
Do they know about me?
他们知道我吗？
Olivia, have you noticed something?
奥莉维亚，你注意到了吗
That you're never taken to meet the begum and the ladies.
土邦王从来不带你去见女王和王妃们
I've met them, thank you.
我已经见过她们了，谢谢你
It was hard going.
挺煎熬的
Nevertheless, it's a discourtesy.
尽管如此，但这很失礼
- To whom?
对谁失礼？
- To you, to you my dear.
对你啊，亲爱的
Even had a quarrel with him about it, about you.
我和他为这事还吵了一架，关于你
- I asked him straight out.
我直接问他
- What?
什么？
Why don't take Olivia, Mrs Rivers, to meet the begum?
你为什么不带奥莉维亚里弗斯夫人见女王？
- And he...
然后他
- What?
他怎么了？
You know what he's like when he doesn't want to answer something.
你知道的，当他不想回答的时候，他就会这样
He laughs and if you keep on he makes you feel a fool and prim
笑呵呵的，如果你一直问，他会让你觉得自己像个傻子
and stupid for asking such a question.
问了一个愚蠢的问题
He's very good at that.
他很擅长伪装
But Harry, I don't want to meet the begum.
但是哈里，我不想去见女王
I can't be friends with her, can I?
我又不能和她成为朋友，不是吗
Not with someone who doesn't speak the same language.
你无法和一个语言不通的人成为朋友
I enjoy being here with you and him, of course.
我喜欢和你待在这儿，当然还有他
I mean, as your friend.
我是说，作为你们的朋友
We have a good time.
我们相处得很开心
Oh, don't look like that, Harry.
哦，哈里不要那个表情
Now you're being like everyone else making me feel I don't understand.
现在你看起来就像另外一个人，让我觉得我看不懂你
Olivia, shall I tell you something?
奥莉维亚，我能和你说实话吗？
I don't think you ought to be coming here.
我觉得你不该来这儿
In fact, I wish you wouldn't.
事实上，我希望你从来没来过
But Harry, I come to see you.
但是哈里，我是来看你的
Of course, naturally, me.
你当然是来看我的
You're awake.
你还没睡？
I saw your light.
我看见你房间的灯还亮着
It's bad for you to read this late.
这么晚看信对你眼睛不好
I suppose you want to be my very good friend again.
我猜你又想成为我非常好的朋友了
Do you mind?
你介意吗？
What a shock he'd have if he knew.
要是让他知道了，他会吓到的
I was due on the eighth,
我的生理期是8号
the 15th, the 22nd,
15号，22号
that's more than two weeks overdue, isn't that wonderful?
推迟了两周，不是什么好兆头吧？
It's my own fault, I should've taken care.
都是我的错，我应该小心一点儿的
Thinking again?
又在想事情？
On the contrary not thinking at all, just letting whatever happens happen.
恰恰相反，我什么都没想，就让一切顺其自然吧
Please wait for me here.
请在这儿等我
They still have that tent, Mrs Rivers
里弗斯夫人，他们现在仍然保留着那个帐篷
and the blood is so fresh and new it's as if it had only happened yesterday.
鲜红的血液，仿佛一切发生在昨天
- Oh.
哦
- Did you have a bad dream?
你做噩梦了？
- Are they gone?
他们走了？
- Who?
谁？
Those men.
那些男人
Who were they?
他们是谁？
I've told Maji about being pregnant.
我告诉玛姬我怀孕了
She's a midwife
她是个助产士
and said if I want an abortion she might try,
她告诉我，如果我想堕胎，她也许可以试一试
with just a massage.
只需要一次简单的按摩
I said "All right let's try".
我回答，好的，我们试一试
She said I was about seven weeks gone so it would be easy now.
她说我才怀孕七周，现在堕胎很容易。
She knew many ways, but at this stage
她知道很多种办法，但目前这个阶段
a simple massage could do it.
有一种简单的按摩方法
No, Maji, no, Maji, no.
不，玛姬，不玛姬，不要
I asked her over and over.
我一次又一次地问她
"You didn't really do anything, did you? Nothing will happen?"
你没有真的做什么，是吧？胎儿也没事，是吧？
And she assured me no, she didn't, "No, it wouldn't."
她向我保证，她什么都没做，胎儿没事
Then she asked me, "You want the child?"
接着她问我，你想留下这个孩子？
And I said, "Yes I do, I do."
我回答她，我想，我想要，我想要
Darling, Olivia, are you partaking?
亲爱的奥莉维亚，你喝酒吗？
- Major?
梅杰？
- Yes, please.
是的
Well.
好吧
To our charming hostess who has elected to stay with us
敬我们美丽的主人，在瘟疫爆发的时候
through our ordeal far down in the plague.
选择和我们一起共度难关
Yes, rather.
是的，非常勇敢。
Here, here.
干杯，干杯
But Major, aren't you due for a spot of leave in the hills?
但是梅杰，你不是要休假去山里避暑吗？
Yes, but this is not the time to go.
是的，但现在不是时候
Our friend the Nawab has been acting up again
我们的朋友土邦王又在挑事了
and I'm afraid things are coming to a head.
我怕事态会控制不住
At present I wouldn't like to be in that boy's shoes.
目前我还不太清楚这个家伙在打什么主意
Which boy's shoes?
哪个家伙？
Our friend.
我们的朋友
I trust Simla isn't gonna dillydally any further over him.
我相信他不会去西米拉那么远的地方消磨时光的
It's certainly time he was taught a lesson.
是时候给他点儿颜色看看了
You talk as if he's a school boy.
你说的好像他是个不听话的学生
Ah, I wish it were that harmless.
啊，我希望他不是个危险的学生
Olivia, he's a dangerous ruffian.
奥莉维亚，他是个危险的暴徒
Those dacoits of his are running around killing and maiming
他手下的那些强盗在他的保护下
with his blessing, under his protection.
四处残害良民
He's a menace to himself, to us,
他不仅对我们是个危险人物，对他自己
and to the wretched inhabitants of his wretched little state.
对那个可怜的国家，人民也是个危险人物
He's the worst sort of ruler.
他是最危险的统治者
The worst sort of Indian you could have.
可能是你见过的最危险的统治者
Dear lady, are you leaving us?
亲爱的女士，你要离开了吗？
To your brandy and cigars.
远离你们的白兰地和雪茄
She's very plucky.
她真的很勇敢
I believe it went up to 118 today.
我觉得今天的温度达到118华氏度了
All right Rivers, better go and see how she is.
里弗斯，没关系的，你还是去看看她吧
Will you mind, sir? I think I ought to.
先生们，失陪一下，我去看看她
So, they are setting up a committee of inquiry?
这么说，他们成立了一个调查委员会？
Yes.
是的
And I'm rather afraid...
恐怕他们打算
they'll be putting our Nawab out of business
把我们的土邦王踢出局
which is a pity,
真遗憾
because there's no denying he has a quality.
因为不可否认的是他本质不坏
He is a prince.
他可是个王子
Yes, but the trouble is, his little state isn't quite princely enough to satisfy him.
没错，问题是他那个小国家，不足以满足他王子般的需求
Poor fellow is tremendously bored.
可怜的家伙是太无聊了
I think he'd do anything to amuse himself.
我觉得他会做任何事愉悦自己
Olivia.
奥莉维亚
What is it?
你怎么了？
I ought to tell you.
我应该告诉你的
It isn't just the heat.
不仅是天气热的原因
What is it? Tell me.
那是什么，快告诉我
Are you ill?
你生病了吗？
Olivia.
奥莉维亚
The fact is, I'm pregnant.
其实，我怀孕了
Darling.
亲爱的
Darling, it's what we want, more than anything.
亲爱的，孩子 是我们最想要的
Yes, of course it is.
是的，当然了
Good morning.
早上好
I'll have to keep bringing more Dickens for Mr Hamilton-Paul.
我给汉密尔顿保罗先生又拿了几本狄更斯的书
We're on Our Mutual Friend now.
我们在看我们共同的朋友
Ah.
啊
He can't seem to get enough of foggy London...
他似乎欣赏不够伦敦的雾色
...and Christmas revels.
和圣诞的狂欢
- Isn't it extraordinary?
是不是很奇怪
- Yes indeed, extraordinary.
是的，确实很奇怪
It was all so murky, both sides intriguing.
一切都是暗箱操作，双方都在密谋策划
The British too, they were playing their own game,
英国人也一样，他们只想参与属于他们自己的游戏
they always did.
他们一向如此
They'd set up some sort of committee to depose him.
他们成立了某种委员会罢黜了他
"Put him out of business" was the facetious phrase they used.
他们的官方术语是踢出局，很滑稽
And, for his successor, they'd picked out some halfwit,
他们任命了他妹妹的儿子
epileptic nephew.
那个患有癫痫症的傻外甥
He was the son of the Nawab's sister.
继承王位
That of course was because the Nawab had no son of his own.
当然也是因为土邦王自己没有子嗣
As it turned out in the end
结果我最后
it was more convenient to drop the nephew than simply to swallow up the whole state
罢黜这个外甥提供了便利，轻而易举地将整个国家
into British India.
纳入英国殖民的印度地区
How dare they appoint anyone to inquire into my activities.
他们怎敢派人调查我的行踪？
I told him. I told your Major Minnies.
我告诉他了，告诉你的梅杰・明尼
Why mine?
为什么是我的？
No, of course not, you have nothing to do with it.
不，当然不是你的，和你一点儿关系都没有
Anyway I made it very clear that from now I shall deal with the viceroy, personally.
不管怎样，我表明了我的态度，从现在起，我要亲自和总督交涉
I told him.
我和他说了
I don't deal with underlings Major Minnies.
我不喜欢梅杰・明尼这群党羽
I know what this is all about.
我知道这一切是为了什么
I know why they hate me, because I don't say, "Yes, Your Excellency."
我知道他们为什么恨我，因为我不说，阁下，遵命
"Very good, Your Excellency."
非常好，阁下
"How right and true, Your Excellency."
你说的没错，阁下
I have something to tell you.
我有个消息要告诉你
What is it?
什么消息？
What is it? Tell me.
什么消息？告诉我
Can't you guess?
你不能猜猜吗？
I'm pregnant.
我怀孕了
You're made to bear a child.
你注定要怀孕的
Are you afraid?
你害怕吗？
Don't be afraid.
别害怕
Now they'll see.
现在他们等着瞧吧
- Who'll see?
谁？
- Major Minnies and the rest of them.
梅杰・明尼还有其他人
They'll laugh out of the other sides of their mouths
当他们见到我儿子的时候
when they see my son.
会笑的前仰后合
Do you mean because...
你的意思是……
of the colour?
肤色的原因吗？
Oh, they'll get the shock of their little English lives.
哦，他们会为这个英国小生命而震惊的
No, no.
不，不
You mustn't go.
你不能离开
I want you to stay here, you must.
我希望你留下来，你必须留下来
My son must be born here in my house.
我的儿子必须在我的房子里出生
How can you be so sure?
你怎么能这么肯定呢？
I'm very sure, absolutely.
我就是很肯定，非常确定
He's mine.
他就是我的儿子
He couldn't not be.
不可能是别人的
What about Douglas?
道格拉斯呢？
He's as sure as you are, and he's my husband.
他和你一样肯定，他还是我的丈夫
What have I done?
我都做了什么？
What have you made me do?
你都让我做了什么？
How do you know it'll be a he?
你怎么知道是个男孩儿呢
Oh, I'm pretty sure.
我非常确定
And he'll do something decent too, you'll see.
你看着吧，他将来会从事非常体面的工作
I must ask my sister to send the Rivers' christening robe.
我要让我姐姐把里弗斯家的洗礼长袍寄过来
All the Rivers babies are christened in it.
里弗斯家的孩子都是穿着它接受洗礼的
You know, they're all very blond.
你知道的，他们都是金发碧眼
We all have white blond hair 'til we're about 12.
十二岁以前，我们的头发都是银色的
Look, I'm sorry.
听着，我很抱歉
What a stupid ass I am to bring you here.
我是个笨蛋，竟然带你来这儿
We won't come back again.
我们再也不来这儿了
Come on darling, let's go.
亲爱的，别哭了，我们走吧
I can hardly find an abortionist for you.
我找不到一个能帮你堕胎的人
Ask your friends in the purdah quarters.
问问你那些营房里的朋友
Ask the begum.
还有女王
It'll be easy enough for her.
对她来讲，轻而易举
Easier than poisoned garments any day.
比用衣服毒死人容易多了
I couldn't refuse her.
我无法拒绝她
I didn't want to see this baby born any more than she did.
我和她一样不想这个孩子出生
No one did, except the Nawab and Douglas.
没人想，除了土邦王和道格拉斯
The begum was glad to help.
女王非常愿意帮忙
She wanted no complications with the British on the one hand
她既不想跟英国扯上关系，也不想
nor did she fancy a little Eurasian heir.
有一个欧亚混血的继承人
Of course, there had to be the utmost secrecy
当然这是最高机密
because if the Nawab had ever found out
因为一旦被土邦王发现了
he'd have killed someone.
他会杀了所有人
He believed 'til the end that it was a natural miscarriage.
一直到最后，他都相信是自然流产
She had begun to bleed the same night
当晚她就开始流血
and Douglas took her to the hospital.
道格拉斯带她去了医院
Well, my young madam.
我可怜的女士
But Dr Saunders was all too familiar with the methods
但桑德斯医生非常熟悉
used by Indian midwives to procure abortions.
印度助产士的堕胎手段
I never knew how she got from the hospital to the palace.
我一直都不知道她是如何从医院逃到皇宫的
A distance of nine miles.
那可是九英里的距离
And she could hardly have walked it in the middle of the night
她刚堕胎，失血过多，那种状态几乎不可能
and her condition with all that loss of blood from her abortion.
在半夜里行走
She'd borrowed some servant's sari in the hospital.
她在医院向一个仆人借来纱丽
She reminded me of one of those mutiny prints.
这让我想起了当时的一则暴乱新闻
I think it's called "Mrs Secombe In Flight from the Mutineers".
我记得一名叫斯科姆太太的女人从暴徒手中逃了出来
Now Mrs Secombe was also in native dress
当时斯科姆太太穿着本地服装
and in a state of agitation.
焦虑不安
Olivia was in flight as well,
奥莉维亚也是一样的
but of course, in the opposite direction,
只不过是逃往了相反的方向
from the civil station at Satipur
从赛提普的中心医院
to the Nawab's palace at Khatm.
逃到了土邦王的哈塔姆皇宫
Chid, you look absolutely awful.
奇德，你看起来糟透了
I think I'm gonna die.
我想我快死了
His liver's affected.
他的肝和肾
And his kidneys too, sit up.
都被感染了，坐起来
What does he expect?
他在想什么
Even I wouldn't think of eating and living the way he has done.
即使我也不能想象像他那样的吃饭和生活
My prescription for him is to put him on the next plane home
我给他的建议是马上乘飞机回家
and the sooner the better.
越快越好
My dear young man, your body's not made to live the life of a holy man.
亲爱的年轻人，你的身体不是让你以圣人的方式生活的
Psst. Let's go.
嘘，我们走吧
What about you, when are you going?
你呢，打算什么时候离开？
Don't know, I haven't made any plans.
不知道，我还没有计划
When my money runs out I suppose.
也许等我没钱的时候吧
I'm staying with my Aunt Betty in Iowa, Washington Iowa.
我会和爱荷华州的贝蒂阿姨住在一起，华盛顿的爱荷华州
It's the cleanest city in the whole USA.
那是全美国最干净的城市
It's a fact, it won a prize for it.
事实上，它还因此得过奖
You should see my Aunt Betty's bathroom.
你们应该去看看我阿姨贝蒂的卫生间
Everything matches, the shower curtain, the bath mat, the toilet paper,
一切都搭配得体，浴帘，防滑垫，厕纸
the little woolly cover on the toilet seat.
甚至是马桶座上的小木盖
Everything's green.
一切都是绿色的
Clean fresh green.
干净清新的绿色
Have a safe journey.
一路平安
If you think the bathrooms clean, you ought to see the kitchen!
要是你觉得卫生间很干净，那你该去看看厨房
- Take care.
保重
- Everything's clean fresh green!
一切都是干净清新的绿色
Goodbye, Chid, bye bye.
拜拜，奇德，拜拜
I knew she was rotten from the first day I saw her.
我第一天见到太多的时候就发现他不简单
Well she wasn't a bad sort, just the wrong type to come out here.
但她不是那种坏人，只不过看起来像坏人
Her embroidery and her piano.
她会刺绣和弹钢琴
That's all very nice at home, it'll hardly due for Satipur.
家里的陈设很干净，但到了赛提普就不一样了
She killed her own baby.
她杀死了自己的孩子
- Oh come, come, Joan.
琼，别这么说
- She could have a baby,
她可以留下这个孩子的
and she killed it.
但她堕掉了
Don't forget, my dear, whose baby it was.
亲爱的，不要忘了那是谁的孩子
What does that matter as long as...
那有什么关系呢，只要……
as long as she cared for him?
只要她在乎他
I just can't stop thinking about it.
我只是忍不住去想这个孩子
Come along, Joan, it's time I got you home.
琼，过来，我们该回家了
Bed for you, my dear.
亲爱的贝德福特
Those are doctor's orders.
谨遵医嘱
- Goodnight, goodnight.
晚安
- Goodnight Joan.
晚安，琼
Now you take good care of yourself, Joan.
好好照顾自己，琼
I will, thank you.
我会的，谢谢你
- Goodnight.
晚安
- Night.
Well, she may have cared for him, but I don't think that your precious Nawab
好吧，她可能在乎他，但我觉得你那位尊贵的土邦王
has returned the compliment.
回绝了她的关心
What a bounder to have taken his revenge in that way.
以这种方式进行报复，他也太残忍了
- Was it only revenge?
仅仅是报复吗？
- Do you doubt it?
你不这么认为吗？
No, I suppose not, not really.
不，我不这么认为
How is Rivers taking it?
里弗斯怎么样了
Like a Stoic and a Roman.
既像一个禁欲者又像一个罗马人
He's a splendid chap.
他是个了不起的家伙
I've sent him on tour to get him away from this place for a while.
我派遣他外出了，暂时离开这里一段时间
He picked the wrong girl.
他选错了伴侣
I'm so immensely fond of him, I wish I could...
我非常了解他，我希望他能
What, match-making already?
什么，已经开始做媒了？
Oh, my dear man, that's what a burra memsahib's for.
哦，亲爱的，我可是善意的
Poor Olivia.
可怜的奥莉维亚
She was a fine looking girl, too.
她曾经长得很漂亮
Was? She's not dead.
曾经？她又没去世
As good as.
最好是这样
The Chowkidar told me that a long time ago
这个看房子的男人告诉我，很久以前
an English memsahib lived here.
有一个英国女人住在这里
She lived completely alone, then she died.
一直孤身一人，直到去世
That was 20 or 30 years ago.
大概二三十年以前的样子吧
Now the house belongs to the Nawab's great nephew
现在这个房子属于土邦王的甥孙
who's a general in the Indian army.
现在掌管印度的军队
He comes here every summer with his family.
他每年夏天都和家人来这里
He came out to see her about two or three times a year.
他大概一年去看她两三次
The rest of the time he was mostly in London
剩下的大多数时间都在伦敦
trying to get his deposition annulled.
试图取消他的罢黜
His mother came to live in London, too.
他的妈妈也去了伦敦
She bought a house in Park Lane, which they've since pulled down.
在公园路买了一处房子，罢黜后他们一直住在那里
It was said that she'd taken the state jewels with her,
据说她带走了国家的珠宝
but it could never be proved,
但无从考证
nor could they get a single pearl away from her.
他们也没从她身上找到一件珠宝
They tried to bring a case against her, but to no avail.
他们想起诉她，但被判无效
Except every time a summons came,
不过每次传票来的时候
the Nawab got himself worked up.
土邦王都会非常暴躁
He'd roar and stamp around.
跺着脚，怒吼着
Then one day, quite suddenly, in his mother's flat, just like that.
后来有一天，在他母亲的公寓里，非常地突然，他就那样去世了
I don't know how long it was
我不知道过了多久
before news reached her that he wouldn't be coming anymore.
她才得知，他再也不会来看她了
Even after she knew, she never went down again
即便她知道了，她也没有下山
but stayed by herself in the house he had bought for her.
而是一个人生活在他给她买的房子里
Namaste.
修道院
The monastery?
修道院？
Would you like me to take you over there?
我带你过去怎么样？
Are you going?
你也去修道院？
- Yes, I am going there.
是的，我要去
- Thank you.
谢谢你
May I help you to...
我帮你拿背包吧
They have a little hospital up here.
这上面有个小医院
That's where Olivia went in the end.
那就是奥莉维亚最后去的意愿
They've agreed to let me come there for my baby.
他们同意我在这儿生下我的宝宝